Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, חודש טוב, Chodesh tov, מרחשון טוב Marheshvan
tov I guess. All right, we pick up at today's דף כ,
Daf Kaf, we're a good עמוד amud behind, we pick up at
the very bottom of י"ט עמוד א. Yud-Tet Amud Aleph. We had
just spent a lot of yesterday dealing with Rabbi Oshaya's read that
Rabbi Shimon
who says,
who is not bothered by the case of אשת אחיו שלא היה
בעולמו, Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya Be'olamo,
that and Rabbi Oshaya tried to claim in all cases which was
a very hard conceptual and based on the משנה Mishna read. We're
now with רב פפא Rav Pappa who says no, no, no. The
only case Rabbi Shimon is not concerned about is when the brother
Shimon, Reuven was married, Reuven was married to Rachel, Reuven died, then
Shimon did יבום yibbum and only then was Levi born, and that's
when Rabbi Shimon says, "Oh, so if Levi is born and Rachel's
already married to Shimon, then the Reuven thing goes away and that's
why he doesn't have a problem." So that's what we're up to
now is רב פפא Rav Pappa who's the reasonable read of the
משנה Mishna and also the logical, you know, conceptually logical position. So
let's pick up from that about eight lines from the bottom, line
starts with word לטעמיה Letaameih is the beginning of the ברייתא, Braita,
okay, of the beginning of the line. רב פפא אמר: Rav Pappa
Amar: ביבם ואחר כך נולד פליג רבי שמעון. Biyavam Ve'achach Nolad Palig
Rabbi Shimon. Rabbi Shimon disagrees when first Shimon did יבום yibbum with
Rachel and then Levi was born. So then Levi says there's no
problem, it's not אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya
Be'olamo, we don't care about Reuven anymore, we look at Rachel in
relationship to
Shimon. אבל נולד ואחר כך יבם, Aval Nolad Ve'achach Yavam, if Levi
was born and then Shimon did יבום yibbum with Rachel, לא פליג,
Lo Palig, he does not disagree.
ותרתיהו לרבנן איצטריך Ve'tarvayu Le'rabbanan Itztrich and both משניות, Mishnayot, the first
and the second, were said for the Rabbis. The first משנה, Mishna,
which was the case where Levi was born and then Shimon did
יבום, yibbum, וזו אף זו קתני, Vezu Af Zu Katani, and it
said A and without saying B. So the Rabbis say that it
is a problem when Levi is born, I'm sorry,
וזו אף זו קתני, Vezu Af Zu Katani, right. So not only
the Rabbis say that case is a problem, but they even say
the second case of the משנה Mishna is a problem, even when
first there's יבום yibbum and then Levi is born. But that second
case, when first there's יבום yibbum and then Levi is born, that
in that case Rabbi Shimon does disagree and say it's not a
problem. Okay, yes.
Can you explain why if Levi is born before Shimon does יבום
yibbum it's a problem?
Yes,
because he's
a contemporary brother, right?
Why with Shimon, but that is in terms of his status with
Rachel. So we go again, let me turn that display thing, sorry,
God willing by today we'll have this other whiteboard up. But anyway,
okay, we turn it on, yeah exactly, again.
Okay,
we have Reuven married to Rachel and Shimon is around, right? That's
stage one. Stage two is that Reuven has died and, sorry, stage
two is that Reuven has died
and now you have Shimon here and Rachel around and Rachel is...
Levi isn't around right now, right? So
Rachel vis-a-vis Levi, vis-a-vis a future brother, Rachel is going to be
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya Be'olamo, אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו.
Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya
Be'olamo.
Okay, and then
stage
three is Levi is born. So then this, now that Levi is
born, that's her relationship to Levi. Okay, and then stage four is
that Shimon does יבום yibbum with Rachel. So in this stage, he's
done יבום yibbum with Rachel, Rachel has already been tagged for Levi
as אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya Be'olamo. So
Rachel remains אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו Eishet Achiv Shelo Haya Be'olamo
for Levi, because that's the status she had at stage three. That
doesn't change just because now Shimon married her. Okay? But if Shimon
had done יבום yibbum up here, if Shimon had done יבום yibbum
up here, then Rachel would have... her past history with Reuven would
have been irrelevant. The way we would have looked at her when
Levi came into the world would have been as Shimon's wife. But
now when Levi comes into the world and you ask who's Rachel?
When Levi is born and you want to ask, "Hey Levi, who
is this woman Rachel?" So when here when he's born, if he's
born at this stage, he says, "Oh, that woman Rachel, that was
Reuven's ex-wife, that was Reuven's widow, אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו." Eishet
Achiv Shelo Haya Be'olamo. But if Shimon did יבום yibbum up here,
and you say, "Hey Levi, who's Rachel?" He'd say, "Oh, it's my
brother Shimon's wife." Right? So her whole status changes in relationship to
Levi. All right, thank you so much. So, I gotta put now
my cuff back down. We're going. Okay, so now all right, so
okay, תניא כוותיה דרב פפא *Tanya kevataiah deRav Pappa*, we turned to
we taught a ברייתא Braita... *Baraita* like רב Rav פפא *Rav Pappa*
ותיובתא דרבי אושעיא *u'tiyuvta deRabbi Oshaya* and a contradiction to רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya *Rabbi Oshaya*.
Again,
that's the only case that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* disagrees
with is when יבום yibbum *Yibum* occurs before לוי Levi *Levi* was
born. שני אחים בעולם b'olamo אחד *Shnei achim ba'olam echad*, two brothers
are alive at the same time. ומת u-meis, אחד מהם בלא ולד
*u'met echad mehem belo valad*, and one of them dies, ראובן Reuven
*Reuben* dies without a kid. ועמד השני הזה לעשות מאמר mamar. ביבמתו
*ve'amad hasheni hazeh la'asot ma'amar bivemanto*, and שמעון Shimon *Shimon* gets all
ready to do מאמר mamar *ma'amar* with רחל Rachel *Rachel*. ולא הספיק
לעשות בה מאמר mamar *velo hispik la'asot bah ma'amar* עד שנולד לו
אח *ad shenolad lo ach* until לוי Levi *Levi* is born, ומת
u'met, *umet*. So that's case number one
is gonna be a couple of cases, so I'll have to draw
that. This ברייתא braita *Baraita*, okay?
Again, anybody understands who שמעון Shimon. *Shimon*, לוי Levi *Levi*, ראובן Reuven.
*Reuben* and שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* and לוי Levi *Levi* are, right? So
case number one in this ברייתא braita. *Baraita* is case case number
one in this ברייתא *Baraita* is that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* wanted to
do מאמר mamar *ma'amar* but basically he didn't. So absolutely nothing that
happened between שמעון Shimon *Shimon* and רחל Rachel? *Rachel*. Okay, here he
wanted to do מאמר mamar *ma'amar*. Who the heck cares what he
wanted to do? We'll discuss in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. But basically
he did nothing and then what does it say? So ולא הספיק
לעשות בה מאמר mamar עד שנולד לו אח *velo hispik la'asot bah
ma'amar ad shenolad lo ach*, and then לוי Levi *Levi* is born.
Okay, and then after לוי Levi *Levi* is born, שמעון Shimon *Shimon*
dies. So what's רחל Rachel *Rachel*? אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. *Eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo*, right? Right? אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo *Eshet achiv shelo
hayah be'olamo* is רחל Rachel *Rachel* with no relationship to שמעון Shimon.
*Shimon*, right? That's all she is, אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo *eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo*. So in that
case, okay, ומת הראשונה יוצאה משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. *umet harishonah yotzah mishum eshet achiv shelo hayah
be'olamo*. והשנייה חולצת או מתייבמת Choletzet o mityabemet. *vehasheniyah choletzet o mityabemet*,
and שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s also married to שרה Sarah *Sarah*. So in
this case where where nothing happened and then he died and then
לוי Levi *Levi* is then born,
okay, לוי Levi *Levi* is born and then he dies. Let me
draw this really quickly. Okay, so we'll call this case A. Case
A, so I'm gonna have to do one, two, or three again
to show the chronology. But this is stage one, stage two לוי
Levi *Levi* is born, stage three is שמעון Shimon *Shimon* dies. Okay,
so שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* now dies and he was married to שרה
Sarah, *Sarah* and רחל Rachel *Rachel* and רחל Rachel *Rachel* he was
not married to. רחל Rachel *Rachel* was just hanging here from ראובן
Reuven, *Reuben*. So in this case רחל Rachel *Rachel* is אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo *eshet achiv shelo hayah
be'olamo*. שמעון Shimon *Shimon* did nothing with רחל Rachel *Rachel*. So she
just walks away, ערוה ervah *ervah*. And שרה Sarah, *Sarah* and שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* is not related to רחל Rachel *Rachel*, so רחל Rachel
*Rachel* doesn't impact שרה Sarah, *Sarah*'s status as a צרה tzara. *tzarah*
because he didn't do anything to רחל Rachel. *Rachel*. So לוי Levi
*Levi* does יבום yibbum *Yibum* or חליצה khalitzah. *Chalitzah* with שרה Sarah.
*Sarah*. Okay? So that's simple case number one, which is שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* did nothing.
Why is the second one חולצת או מתייבמת choletzes o misyabemes, *choletzet
o mityabemet*? השנייה *Hasheniyah* is שרה Sarah, *Sarah*. לוי Levi *Levi* does
either חליצה khalitzah. *Chalitzah* or יבום yibbum *Yibum* to שרה Sarah *Sarah*
because because he was born before שמעון Shimon *Shimon* died. Right. Okay.
All right, so thank you, Charlie. So okay. So שנייה חולצת או
מתייבמת *sheniyah choletzet o mityabemet*. עשה בה מאמר mamar ואחר כך נולד
אח *Asah bah ma'amar ve'achar kach nolad ach* או שנולד אח ואחר
כך עשה בה מאמר v'achar kach asah bah ma'amar *o shenolad ach
ve'achar kach asah bah ma'amar*. If מאמר mamar *ma'amar* was done either
before after לוי Levi *Levi* was born, that doesn't matter. What matters
is before שמעון Shimon *Shimon* died. If מאמר mamar *ma'amar* was done
and then he died, הראשונה יוצאת משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו
eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. *harishonah yotzet mishum eshet achiv shelo hayah
be'olamo*. רחל Rachel, *Rachel* just walks away because of אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. *eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo*.
והשנייה חולצת ולא מתייבמת Choletzet velo mityabemet. *vehasheniyah choletzet velo mityabemet*, and
שרה Sarah, *Sarah* can only do חליצה khalitzah *Chalitzah* and not יבום
yibbum. *Yibum*. So what's case number B? Case number B is the
same except the difference by case number B is is that one
and two are the same, but before you had three you had
2b which is שמעון Shimon *Shimon* did מאמר mamar *ma'amar* with with
רחל Rachel, *Rachel*. Okay, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* did מאמר mamar *ma'amar* with
רחל Rachel *Rachel* sometime before he died. It doesn't matter if it
was before or after לוי Levi *Levi* was born, but sometime before
he died. So in that case, maybe it's even easier just using
this. Scenario B, we'll use the blue. Scenario B is that שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* did מאמר mamar, *ma'amar* with רחל Rachel, *Rachel*. Okay, but
the blue doesn't work.
Okay, I'm sorry about that. I red van, and I red then.
Anyway, if he had done מאמר mamar *ma'amar* with רחל Rachel *Rachel*
sometime before he died, then what would the story be? Then the
story would be that by the time he had died he had
a quasi, right, relationship with רחל Rachel. *Rachel*. And now that he's
dead, so לוי Levi *Levi* obviously can't do anything with רחל Rachel,
*Rachel*. אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo hayah be'olamo *Eshet
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo*, she walks away. But he can't do יבום
yibbum. *Yibum* now with שרה Sarah *Sarah* because that's a quasi צרת
ערוה tzaras ervah. *tzarat ervah*. Not a full צרת ערוה tzaras ervah
*tzarat ervah* because he didn't really consummate the marriage,
it was just מאמר mamar *ma'amar*, but
enough of a quasi צרת ערוה tzaras ervah. *tzarat ervah* because of
the מאמר mamar *ma'amar* that he now cannot do יבום yibbum, *Yibum*
with שרה Sarah, *Sarah*. But he has to do חליצה khalitzah because
דאורייתא d'oraisa he still is obligated, right? When a דרבנן d'rabbanan gets
in the way you still have to do חליצה. khalitzah Is that
clear? Noam looks clear? Okay, so that's case B is when there
was some type of a מאמר. mamar. And if there's some type
of a מאמר mamar, done, then רחל Rachel impacts שרה's Sarah. status.
And then he can no longer do יבום yibbum, with שרה, Sarah,
he can only do חליצה.
khalitzah And what happens to רחל?
Rachel And רחל Rachel. walks away, because he's a total ערווה. ervah.
Okay. Alright, so yes.
The language here is רבי Rebbi אושעיא rather than רב אושעיא. Rav
Oshaya.
Yeah, I know, I don't want to worry about that because it's
whatever because רב and a רבי Rebbi, and whatever. Alright, anyway, רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now in this case we have a
new רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon another problem he has, or a different
position. ביאה או חליצה של אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה. Biah o khalitzah
shel achas meihen poteres tzarasah.
So I will tell you now what he's going to say and
then we'll read it in the גמרא. Gemara. Comes along רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and says in this scenario, okay, basically לוי Levi can
do יבום yibbum or חליצה khalitzah with שרה, Sarah. but רחל Rachel
either way—sorry, scenario B, scenario B since scenario B, yeah, the scenario
B that we're talking about, okay, so he says לוי Levi basically
can do יבום yibbum or חליצה khalitzah with שרה, Sarah. and רחל
Rachel, walks away. Why? Because you might remember from yesterday that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically says if there's זיקה zika plus מאמר mamar
that might be as good as יבום. yibbum, It might be ככנוסה
דמיא. k'knusah damya. Anybody remember that from yesterday? So let's assume that
the מאמר ma'amar. with רחל Rachel made her was like יבום. yibbum,
Okay. So if it was like יבום, yibbum but what happened? If
he did that first, he did that first, and then לוי Levi?
was born. And now it gets confusing, but okay.
And then לוי Levi is born and then שמעון Shimon dies. Okay,
right? So that's what happens. So if he did this, if מאמר
ma'amar is like יבום, yibbum, then according to רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon
other position, if לוי Levi is born after יבום yibbum, or if
that counts as יבום yibbum occurred, then רחל Rachel is okay to
him, right? Because she's now—by the time לוי Levi is born, already
he's in a
מצוות יבום או חליצה mitzvas yibbum o khalitzah one or the other.
So if he had really done יבום, yibbum of course לוי Levi
would be okay. So maybe this counts as יבום, yibbum and then
לוי Levi also is okay. So in that case, he could do,
you know, יבום yibbum with either רחל Rachel or שרה. Sarah, However,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that it's a ספק safek what the
status of מאמר ma'amar. is. So in case this מאמר ma'amar did
not count as יבום, yibbum then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's
nothing. Meaning as opposed to the רבנן Rabbanan that say מאמר ma'amar?
is quasi, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's either all or nothing.
Okay, he's a man of extremes. So if this counted as יבום,
yibum. then לוי Levi is born, both of them are okay, right?
She's already married to שמעון. Shimon Go ahead, do יבום yibum, to
either, or חליצה chalitza to either. If it counted as nothing, then
רחל Rachel irrelevant. So obviously don't do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel
because she's אשת אח שלא היה בעולמו, eishes ach shelo haya b'olamo,
but you can still do יבום yibum. with שרה, Sarah. right? So
basically what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. is saying in this scenario, you
can't do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel because maybe מאמר ma'amar! doesn't
count for anything and maybe she's out of the picture. But in
that case, it wouldn't impact שרה Sarah because if מאמר ma'amar. didn't
count, it's nothing. It's not middle, it's all or nothing. And if
מאמר ma'amar does count, then they're both okay. So in either way,
focus on שרה, Sarah do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with שרה
Sarah? and you're fine. Okay. Is that clear? Yes? Okay, let's read
that in the גמרא. Gemara Alright, ביאה bi'ah או חליצה chalitzah של
אחת מהן—אחת מהן does not mean either one, it means one specific
one of them, שרה, Sarah okay, פוטרת צרתה. poteres tzarasah. חלץ לבעלת
מאמר—now Khalatz l'ba'alas mamar he's going to say it won't do you
any good if you focus on רחל. Rachel If you did חליצה
chalitzah on רחל, Rachel the one who had מאמר, ma'amar. he did
מאמר ma'amar to, לא נפטרה צרה. lo nifterah tzarah. Then you will
not have helped out שרה. Sarah? You will not have helped out,
excuse me,
שרה, Sarah, שרה.
Sarah, Oh God.
Anyway, if you did חליצה chalitzah. on מאמר ma'amar, of רחל, Rachel
that's not going to help because maybe רחל—maybe Rachel this thing is
not a real relationship. So if you did it to רחל, Rachel
it's not going to have an impact on
שרה. Sarah
Okay. לא נפטרה צרה. Lo nifterah tzarah. כנס ומת ואחר כך נולד,
Kinas u'mes v'achar kach nolad, okay, so then that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon So רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon then will say as long as
you focus on שרה, Sarah you're okay because the מאמר ma'amar is
either all or nothing and therefore you're allowed to focus on שרה.
Sarah Alright, now, some people get confused or let's say you did—alright,
let's not worry about that.
Okay, you can make up the דרבנן. d'rabbanan. I'm just trying to
focus enough on the basic case. Alright, so now, third—so first case
is no מאמר.
ma'amar Second case is—so let's just list the types of cases we've
got. Case A is no מאמר, ma'amar and in that case clearly
רחל Rachel and שרה Sarah
have nothing to do with one another. Okay, they're completely unrelated. So
basically the focus is on לוי's Levi relationship or whatever, okay, they're
not related.
Case—well, I guess what I'll do is
I'll do שמעון. Shimon Okay, so
no מאמר ma'amar, in that case, so... In a case of
that case, in that case, we have שמעון Shimon is married to
שרה Sarah and a quasi relationship to רחל. Rachel Okay, that was
case number B. Okay, there was a מאמר. ma'amar Case number three
is any guesses? No מאמר ma'amar to מאמר.
ma'amar This is שמעון Shimon marries שרה?
Sarah Yes,
and that's why it was חליצה chalitzah and not יבום. yibum Case
number three is יבום, yibum okay, where שמעון Shimon is going to
שרה Sarah. and to רחל, Rachel.
and that's the clear case that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon argues on.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Sorry, you're on computer duty there, Charlie.
Okay, so: כנסה ומת ואחר כך
נולד לו
אח.
Kinsah umet ve’achar kach
nolad lo ach.
או
שנולד
לו אח ואחר כך כנסה ומת.
O shenolad lo ach ve’achar
kach kinsah umet. כנסה. Kinsah.
Yes, I did, I forgot the first word. כנסה ומת. Kinsah umet.
Did יבום yibum. and then he died, ואחר כך נולד לו אח.
ve’achar kach nolad lo ach. או שנולד לו אח ואחר כך כנסה
ומת. O shenolad lo ach ve’achar kach kinsah umet. There was יבום.
yibum. שתיהן פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום. Shteihen peturot min hachalitza umin
hayibum.
So in that case, that now, in both of those cases, לוי
Levi was born
before the יבום yibum took place, right? Notice: כנסה ומת. Kinsah umet.
He did יבום yibum and he died and then לוי Levi was
born. או נולד לו אח, O nolad lo ach, or
לוי Levi was born ואחר כך כנסה ומת ve’achar kach kinsah umet
and then he did יבום yibum and he died. So in both
of those cases you have אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eshet achiv
shelo hayah b'olamo Why?
There are three scenarios of יבום yibum in terms of when לוי
Levi is born. Okay, scenario number one is
יבום. yibum,
ראובן Reuven did
יבום. yibum ראובן. Reuven.
שמעון. Shimon
שמעון Shimon did יבום yibum, with רחל Rachel and then שמעון Shimon
died and then לוי Levi is born. In that case, what's רחל
Rachel. to him? אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו
eshet achiv
shelo hayah b'olamo of this brother שמעון, Shimon right? Okay, so in
that scenario everybody agrees that's no good. Scenario number two
is שמעון Shimon, is that לוי Levi is born and then שמעון
Shimon does יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel In that scenario, what's רחל
Rachel, to לוי?
Levi אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo, of
ראובן, Reuven.
right?
Right? Because in this case שמעון Shimon had not changed her status
yet; she was still ראובן's Reuven אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eshes
achiv shelo hayah b'olamo.
In this case, she's אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo
hayah b'olamo, of שמעון Shimon because שמעון Shimon changed her status but
then he died before לוי Levi was born. The only case that
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would disagree with is that שמעון Shimon did
יבום yibum to רחל, Rachel, then לוי Levi was born, and then
שמעון Shimon, died. Okay, and then he comes into the world and
she's in an okay status. All right, so that's what we have.
Those are the three scenarios. Let's read that now. Okay, so: כנסה
ומת
ואחר כך
נולד לו אח.
Kinsah umet ve’achar
kach nolad lo ach. So he did יבום yibum and then he
died and then לוי Levi? is born. When לוי Levi is born,
she's אשת שמעון שלא היה בעולמו. eshet Shimon shelo hayah be'olamo. או
שנולד לו אח, O shenolad lo ach, לוי Levi is born before
יבום, yibum so she was אשת ראובן שלא היה בעולמו, eshet Reuven
shelo hayah be'olamo, ואחר כך כנסה ומת, Ve’achar kach kinsah umet, and
then שמעון Shimon decided to יבום yibum and he died. שתיהן פטורות
מן החליצה ומן היבום. Shteihen peturot min hachalitza umin hayibum. So in
that case, everybody agrees that she's a full ערווה, erva, אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו. eshet achiv shelo hayah b'olamo She's ערווה erva and
the other wife is an ערווה erva and every or צרת ערווה
tzarat erva everybody walks away. Now: כנסה, Kinsah, שמעון Shimon did יבום,
yibum ונולד לו אח, venolad lo ach, and then לוי Levi was
born. So when לוי Levi came into the world, רחל Rachel was
okay, was שמעון's Shimon wife, ואחר כך מת, ve’achar kach met, and
then שמעון Shimon died. That case, according to the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, same thing: שתיהן פטורות מן החליצה ומן היבום דברי רבי מאיר.
Shteihen peturot min hachalitza umin hayibum divrei Rebbi Meir. Doesn't change her
status according to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. She's still אשת אח eshet
ach because of ראובן. Reuven ורבי שמעון אומר הואיל ובאה מצווה בהיתר,
VeRebbi Shimon omer ho'il uva'ah mitzvah beheter, since when לוי Levi. was
born, he came into the world and she was in an okay
status, she was שמעון's Shimon wife, ולא עמדה עליו שעה אחת באיסור,
velo amda alav sha'ah achat be'issur, and she never had a status
to him of אשת אחיו eshet achiv. שלא היה בעולמו. In that
case, she's totally okay. מיבם לאיזה מהם שירצה וחולץ לאיזה מהם שירצה.
Meyabem le'eizeh mehem sheyirtzeh vecholeitz le'eizeh mehem sheyirtzeh. You could do יבום
yibum or חליצה chalitzah. to either one. Okay, and now the גמרא
Gemara, just spells it out one minute. הא דבסיפא למאן קתני לה?
Ha de'besifa leman katani lah? The third case, which we just said
is the one רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon sort of showed his disagreement
with, that she first did יבום yibum. and then לוי Levi, was
born, why are we mentioning the third case? אילימא לרבי מאיר, Ilima
leRebbi Meir, if it's just for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir purposes to
say רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir disagrees, says it's a problem in all
three cases, קתני למה לי? katani lamah li? לא שנא ליה לרבי
מאיר בין יבם ואחר כך נולד בין נולד ואחר כך יבם. Lo
shanya leh leRebbi Meir bein yibam ve’achar kach nolad bein nolad ve’achar
kach yibam. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir in all of the three
scenarios, it's the same הלכה. halacha. It's always אשת אחיו eshes achiv
שלא היה בעולמו for ראובן. Reuven לערבינהו וליתנינהו. Le'arvinhu uleitaninhu. Why not
mention all three scenarios? The way the ברייתא... it first said the
first two scenarios and said these two are no good and then
it said the third scenario and said this is no good and
Rabbi שמעון Shimon says it is good. So what the גמרא, Gemara
all the גמרא's Gemara proving, right remember Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua said that
Rabbi שמעון Shimon disagreed with all the scenarios. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying if Rabbi שמעון Shimon? disagreed with all the scenarios, why
did it mention first these two no good and then the third
one no good and Rabbi שמעון Shimon disagreed? Just put all three
of them together. The fact that you had this third scenario as
a separate הלכה halakha is showing that that's the only one that
Rabbi שמעון Shimon disagrees with. So if it really was true that
they were that Rabbi שמעון Shimon disagreed with everything, וליתנינהו וליסנינהו, u'litninhu
u'lisninhu, just mix them all together and say all three scenarios at
the same time.
אלא לאו Ella lav Rabbi שמעון, Shimon it must be the third
scenario said just because that is the only scenario that Rabbi שמעון
Shimon disagrees with. וביבום באחר נולד פליגי בנולד באחר יבום
לא פליגי. U'biyibum b'achar nolad pligi, b'nolad b'achar yibam lo pligi. But
so there and when first יבום yibum took place and then לוי
Levi is born, that's the one case he disagreed with. Because then
when לוי Levi. comes into the world, רחל's Rachel? status is already
now שמעון's Shimon. wife. But if he was first born and then
יבום yibum took place, לוי Levi, would not disagree with that then
when he comes into the... שמעון Shimon would not disagree then she's
already אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו to לוי Levi and that case
he would agree with. שמע מינה. Shma mina. So finally the גמרא
Gemara says phew okay good we've proven what should have been obvious
from the very beginning which is that Rabbi שמעון Shimon, only disagrees
in the scenario where first there's יבום yibum, and then לוי Levi
is born. Yes, you had a question.
The idea that that שמעון Shimon, could do יבום yibum? with רחל
Rachel and she's still in some way considered ראובן's Reuven wife, isn't
that incredibly problematic?
No, because for שמעון, Shimon for שמעון Shimon that's exactly what the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum. is. שמעון Shimon and ראובן Reuven were
alive at the same time. So yeah, she's ראובן's Reuven dead wife,
she's dead ראובן's Reuven wife, and that's why he has a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום.
yibum, Wait, so to לוי Levi she's like kind of inherit like...
Sure, there's an איסור ערוה issur ervah for your dead brother's wife.
That's the חידוש chiddush of יבום yibum. that you do יבום yibum
in the face of the איסור ערוה issur ervah of dead brother's
wife.
Right, but so to לוי Levi she's שמעון's Shimon wife. Yeah, but
why is she attributed to ראובן Reuven rather than שמעון Shimon in
regards to לוי? Levi That's...
Whoa, whoa, whoa, now I see how you feel when I'm on
the receiving end.
Yes. Say what? Like, my
question about the scenario two. Yeah. So,
so when you're considering what the reason that she's forbidden from לוי
Levi is because she's considered ראובן's Reuven wife.
Because לוי Levi was born after ראובן Reuven? died. Yeah.
So when לוי Levi is born,
שמעון Shimon was was around when ראובן Reuven, was around. So if
לוי Levi is born after שמעון Shimon.
does יבום, yibum, she's more ראובן's Reuven wife than she is שמעון's?
Shimon.
No, she's still, not more. Okay. She doesn't lose the status that
she had vis-a-vis לוי. Levi Once here she's
she's an ערוה ervah. to לוי, Levi then that status continues even
after she gets married. Okay, that's the idea, the status remains. Yes.
Wait, but the whole concept is that he's creating more זכות zchus
for his brother by marrying his brother's childless widow. Yeah. So, how
about his obligation to שמעון?
Shimon,
In which case? What do you mean?
In this case we're suggesting why doesn't לוי Levi. have an obligation
to שמעון Shimon not for him to have children?
Well, she does, except that she's an ערוה.
ervah What if רחל Rachel was his daughter?
What if רחל Rachel? never knew ראובן? Reuven Doesn't matter, רחל's Rachel
an ערוה ervah. to him.
Right because because of שמעון's Shimon wife.
Let's say let's say he never knew
ראובן, Reuven,
let's say he never knew ראובן Reuven but ראובן Reuven had kids,
right? Would you say that oh now he's got to do he's
got to do יבום? yibum, No, because she's an ערוה. ervah Doesn't
matter if he knew ראובן, Reuven רחל's Rachel, an ערוה ervah. to
him.
But if ראובן Reuven had kids then שמעון Shimon never would have...
Well that's true, fine. Okay, let's say he never knew רחל Rachel
because רחל Rachel, was his wife's long long-lost sister, right? It doesn't
matter if he knew or didn't know her, she's an
ערוה. ervah. That's definitely an ערוה. ervah. Right! So here too she's
an ערוה. ervah The ערוה ervah is אשת אחיו. She's ראובן's Reuven
wife. Now that's an ערוה ervah. unless there was a מצוה יבום.
mitzvah yibbum If there wasn't a מצוה יבום, mitzvah yibbum. it's an
ערוה.
ervah But we're actually thinking of her as שמעון's Shimon? wife, not
ראובן's Reuven wife.
But when he was born, he was thinking of her as ראובן's
Reuven wife because when he was born שמעון Shimon? had not yet
done יבום. yibum Oh.
And רחל Rachel never loses that status.
And she never even after she marries שמעון.
Shimon, That's right,
for him it would've been as if
he came into the world...
Exactly, exactly. Now you got it?
Wait but what if she remarried twice or she was married to
somebody after that? Yes.
Does she continue she carries both
statuses
with her? What do you mean?
רחל Rachel will always remain אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו to לוי.
Levi In addition to she's also שמעון's Shimon wife, but she's also
an ערוה ervah, to לוי, Levi she's also אשת ראובן שלא היה
בעולמו. eshet Reuven shelo hayah b'olamo. Alright. Alright, getting a little
clearer? Alright fine. גופא. Gufa. Let's
go back and look at I don't know how the other דף
יומי Daf Yomi manages to keep up keep up with the pace.
Alright, גופא. Gufa. I guess it's either understanding it or keeping up.
All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
not גופא, Gufa, excuse me, אמר מר, Amar Mar, right. OK. So
let's go back and and look at what we've quoted before, right?
That's the difference of אמר מר Amar Mar and גופא. Gufa. אמר
מר Amar Mar is we're going to focus in on a piece
we quoted before. גופא Gufa quotes a whole text when we've only
quoted an excerpt earlier. So אמר מר, Amar Mar, let's go back
and look at an look at something that we were, a piece
of what we were just quoting. עמד השני לעשות מאמר ביבמתו ולא
הספיק לעשות מאמר ביבמתו עד שנולד אח ומת ראשונה יוצאה משום אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו ושניה אוכלת את הסו משבאמת. Amad hashani la'asot
ma'amar bivemto velo hispik la'asot ma'amar bivemto ad shenolad ach umet rishona
yotzea mishum eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo veshniya ochel et haso mishebe'emet.
So that's the simple
case. Simple,
which Shimon did nothing with Rachel and then Shimon died. So in
that case Rachel is אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, she walks away,
and Sarah, Levi can go ahead and do יבום Yibum or חליצה
chalitzah with Sarah. No problem, right? So Rachel's the ערווה ervah because
Levi was born after Reuven died, but Shimon did nothing with Rachel
so she doesn't have an impact on Shimon's other wife, on Sarah.
Every more or less clear to people? Yeah. So now the only
thing the גמרא's Gemara going to ask is why does it say
he was about to do מאמר ma'amar and didn't have a chance
to do מאמר? ma'amar Just say he didn't do מאמר! ma'amar, He
did nothing! OK, so let's take a
look. מאי עמד? Mai amad? He got up to do מאמר. ma'amar
ומאי לא הספיק? U-mai lo hispik? But he didn't have the chance.
אי עבד עבד, I-avad avad, if he did מאמר ma'amar he did
it. ואי לא עבד לא עבד, Ve-i lo avad lo avad, if
he didn't do it he didn't do it. I don't want to
hear any stories, just did you do it or not? אלא, Ella,
so now we're going to say a חידוש chiddush about מאמר. ma'amar
עמד, Amad, what it means is he was getting up to do
מאמר ma'amar was מדעתה, mada'atah, she had initially agreed. She said, "Oh,
let's do a מאמר, ma'amar a קידושין kiddushin that precedes יבום, yibum.
are you interested in this?" and she said yes. ולא הספיק מדעתה,
Velo hispik mada'atah,
he didn't have an opportunity to do it with her agreement. In
the end she changed her mind. And she said, "Wait, I changed
my mind, I don't want to do מאמר ma'amar with you, I
don't want it to lead to יבום, yibum no forget it." She
refused. OK. ולא הספיק מדעתה אלא בעל כרחה, Velo hispik mada'atah ella
be'al karchah, and then in the end he did מאמר ma'amar not
in the way he had intended, עמד, amad, he did מאמר ma'amar
in a different way, he just forced it on her. Not force
sex, that's going to be יבום yibum, which we'll get to. יבום
yibum works בעל כרחה. be'al karchah. But this is forcing the מאמר,
ma'amar. the rabbinic קידושין kiddushin that precedes יבום. yibum, So here's an
interesting question. Do you look at this through the lens of קידושין
kiddushin and therefore it's only good if it's done with her agreement,
or do you look at it as a beginning of the process
of יבום yibum and it would take effect even if it was
done בעל כרחה? be'al karchah? So that's what we're reading in that
scenario to he tried, he was about to and didn't have a
chance, that somehow it was done in the less ideal way.
Just in declaration, right, מאמר ma'amar is just a declaration right? Right.
So we'll see, yeah exactly. So the word מאמר ma'amar means basically
declaration. We'll see exactly what the, you know, what that constitutes, but
yes. So now it says like this,
ודלא כרבי, u-delo ke-Rebbi, not like Rebbi. דתניא ותנא ברייתא, De-tanya u-tana
baraita, העושה מאמר ביבמתו שלא מדעתה, ha-oseh ma'amar bi-vemtto shelo mi-da'atah, somebody
did it without her acquiescence. רבי אומר קנה, Rebbi omer kanah, it's
still binding, again, this rabbinic institution of מאמר ma'amar is binding.
What the consequences are of מאמר ma'amar we've already seen some נפקא
מינות, nafkaminas, is it כנוסה דמי, kenusa damei, etc. So you know,
בדיעבד bedieved if you don't do it and you go straight to
יבום, yibum יבום yibum works, but there are halakhic consequences and חז"ל
Chazal wanted you to do מאמר ma'amar first. So Rebbi said if
it was done בעל כרחה be'al karchah it's still binding. חכמים אומרים
לא קנה, Chachamim omrim lo kanah, it's not
binding. מאי טעמא דרבי? Mai ta'ama de-Rebbi? What's the reason of Rebbi?
גמר מביאה דיבמה, Gamar mi-biah de-yevamah, he learns that from the case
of the actual act of sex with the sister-in-law. מה ביאה דיבמה
בעל כרחה, Mah biah de-yevamah be'al karchah, the same way that works
even if she's not agreeing to יבום, yibum, even not agreeing to
the sex and certainly if she's not agreeing to the desire to
be, you know, for the marriage that results or the relationship that
results. So and obviously this is a very difficult, whole idea that
the rape can be halakhically binding, and we'll get to that later,
but
she's basically considered married to this guy anyway.
Right. So the reason that works, the logic why יבום yibbum, בעל
כרחה be'al karchah works is because since there's a זיקה, zikah, there's
a, there's a sort of, you know, a, a quasi-קידושין kiddushin that
already exists, then the act of יבום yibbum is just seen as
sort of manifesting it. So therefore just the physical reality of them
having had sex... Right. Of course, you could still say a physical
reality of having had sex in a way that has nothing to
do with some type of a marital context and acquiescence or whatever
maybe shouldn't be so relevant, but that's the הלכה. halakhah. It also
works when it's against his will, if he's not aware that this
is his sister-in-law, or the גמרא Gemara even has a funny scenario
where he has an erection and falls off of a roof and
does יבום yibbum. with her un-intending to have sex with her. So
it's not just about against her will, but obviously there's something much
more, you know, deeply disturbing about that scenario. But the same way
that works for יבום, yibbum says Rebbi, אף קידושין דיבמה בעל כרחה,
af kiddushin de-yevamah be'al karchah, the
קידושין kiddushin that we have for the sister-in-law works against her will.
רבנן גמרי מקידושין דעלמא Rabbanan gamri mi-kiddushin de-alma and the rabbis learn
from no, it's a, once we institute... instituted מאמר, ma'amar. we made
it like a standard
קידושין. kiddushin. מה קידושין דעלמא מדעתה אף קידושין דיבמה מדעתה. mah kiddushin
d'alma m'da'atah, af kiddushin d'ivama m'da'atah. And the same way normal קידושין
kiddushin has to be with her acquiescence, so the קידושין kiddushin that
we've created for יבמה yevama has to be with her acquiescence. So
we're assuming that our ברייתא is of that opinion, and the funny
language of אמר ולא הספיק amar v'lo hispik is that scenario and
it's saying it didn't work. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamifligi, what do
they debate? It seems pretty clear what they debate, but okay. מר
סבר מילי דיבמה ממילי דיבמה הוה ליה למילף, mar savar mili d'ivama
mimili d'ivama havah leih l'meilef, since מאמר ma'amar is a יבמה yevama
institution we should apply יבמה yevama types of rules to it. ומר
סבר מילי דקידושין ממילי דקידושין הוה ליה למילף. u-mar savar mili d'kiddushin
mimili d'kiddushin havah leih l'meilef. No, it's what we're creating is a
type of a קידושין kiddushin so we should apply קידושין kiddushin type
of rules. Okay, so that's that section of the ברייתא. Now moving
on, עשה בה מאמר ואחר כך נולד לו אח, asah bah ma'amar
v'achar kach nolad lo ach, or שנסב לו אח ואחר כך עשה
בה מאמר. she-nasav lo ach v'achar kach asah bah ma'amar. Scenario number
two: מאמר ma'amar was done with רחל Rachel and then לוי Levi
was born. ומת, ראשונה יוצאת משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. rishonah
yotzes mishum eshes achiv shelo hayah b'olamo. So since רחל Rachel, was
never really was not really ייבום yibum with שמעון, Shimon so she
walks so he can't do anything with רחל. Rachel, She's an ערוה,
ervah. she walks away, but because she was quasi-married to שמעון, Shimon
it creates like a quasi-צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah, So what are you
going to do with שרה? Sarah. ושנייה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. u-shniyah choletzes
v'lo misyavemes. She does חליצה chalitzah not ייבום. yibum. Okay, because again,
the רבנן Rabbanan hold that this מאמר ma'amar creates a quasi-relationship, enough
to create a problem for שרה, Sarah. so we won't allow ייבום,
yibum, but not enough to let her walk away without חליצה. chalitza
That's the רבנן. Rabbanan. רבי שמעון אומר ביאתו או חליצתו של אחד
מהן פוטרת צרתה. Rebbe Shimon omer bi'aso o chalitzaso shel achad meihen
poteres tzarasah. Rebbe Shimon says, just do ביאה or חליצה chalitza, with
one of them and you're fine. Now it doesn't mean with either
one, it means with one specifically, right, with שרה, Sarah. because רחל's
Rachel status is in doubt, but שרה's Sarah status is clear; it
was אשת שמעון eshes Shimon and he can do ייבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitza So אהייא קאי, a-heiya ka'ei, which one is he referring
to? אילימא אהנולד לו אח, eileima a-hanolad lo ach, which scenario is
he referring to? אילימא אהנולד לו אח, eileima a-hanolad lo ach, if
לוי Levi was first born ואחר כך עשה בה מאמר ma'amar and
then the מאמר ma'amar was done with רחל. Rachel So in that
case, if לוי was first born, then before מאמר ma'amar was done
which might have changed רחל's Rachel status, she already was tagged as
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. So then the מאמר ma'amar would not
change her status, right? And then there would really be a problem
of צרת ערוה ervah in that case. So in that case, הא
אמרת בנולד ולבסוף יבם לא פליג רבי שמעון. ha amarta b'nolad u-l'vasof
yavam lo palig Rebbe Shimon. If first he's born and then ייבום
yibum or this maybe-ייבום-like yibum thing מאמר ma'amar, took place, he would
agree that she remains a problem and then and then שרה Sarah.
would be, you know, צרת ערוה. So you couldn't because she would
clearly be an ערוה. אלא אעשה בה מאמר ואחר כך נולד לו
אח. ela a-asah bah ma'amar v'achar kach nolad lo ach. So what
we're talking about is the scenario that first שמעון Shimon, did מאמר
ma'amar, with רחל, Rachel which might count as a ייבום, yibum, and
then לוי was born. And now we look at it the following
way: חלץ לבעלת מאמר, chalatz l'va'alas ma'amar, if he did חליצה chalitza.
to רחל, Rachel לא נפטרה צרה, lo nifterah tzarah, then that doesn't
help שרה Sarah who's the צרה. Tzarah, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? משום
דהוי צרה ודאי ובעלת מאמר ספק ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. mishum
d'havai tzara vadai u-va'alas ma'amar safeik v'ein safeik motzi midei vadai. Okay,
because now I've just showed you this scenario once more. They actually
שרה Sarah, and עליזה Aliza show up on the board. No, it's
okay, it's still up on the board here because it was מאמר.
Okay, so he did מאמר with רחל Rachel and he's definitely married
to שרה and then לוי is born, right, and then שמעון dies.
So the שרה is definitely שמעון's wife, he definitely has a חיוב
chiyuv of ייבום, yibum, okay, so he can do ייבום yibum or
חליצה chalitza, with שרה. Now how about רחל? Rachel Well, רחל Rachel
מאמר might count as ייבום yibum and then it happened before לוי
was born and then in that scenario she's not צרת ערוה, רחל
Rachel is got totally okay, and in theory he could do it
with either, okay, because but and that's why he's allowed to do
it with שרה. But why can't he do it with רחל? Rachel
Because maybe מאמר counts as nothing, meaning it's no quasi, it's all
or nothing. And if it counts as nothing, then רחל Rachel, is
not married to שמעון and she's אשת ראובן שלא היה בעולמו eshes
Reuven shelo hayah b'olamo and she's a problem. So either מאמר counted
and she totally got כשרה-ed kasher up, רחל, Rachel right, or מאמר
didn't count and she's totally אשת ראובן eshes Reuven and she's not
relevant. So don't do anything with רחל Rachel because you don't know;
either she's a complete ערוה or she's totally okay. So you can't
do anything with רחל, Rachel but you can do something with שרה.
Yeah. What if לוי was born? What? When was לוי born? Before
שמעון died, after שמעון had done מאמר. So why doesn't he become
אשת אחיו שלא why doesn't she become אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו
to him? Sorry, vis-à-vis שמעון. Because first מאמר was done and מאמר
with רחל Rachel might count as ייבום yibum and then לוי is
born. בעולם b'olamo is when he dies. Then then she's אשת אחיו
yeah. No, הוא בעולמו, hu b'olamo, he was living at the same
time of שמעון. בעולם is previous. So רשב"א Rashba is either totally
okay or totally ערווה, ervah, but he doesn't do anything to impact
שרה. But a חליצה Chalitzah to רחל won't help because רחל might
be irrelevant and therefore שרה won't do anything for שרה. Okay. Okay.
So that's why it says, don't do something with רחל, he says,
חלץ לבעלת מאמר לא נפטרה שרה. chalatz l'ba'alas ma'amar lo niftara Sarah.
If you did it with רחל, you didn't do anything. Why? מאי
טעמא? משום דהוי שרה ודאי רחל ספק. Mai ta'ama? Mishum d'hava Sarah
vaday, Rachel safeik. I'm sorry, שרה's status is definite. She is definitely
אשת שמעון. Eshes Shimon. Okay. ובעלת מאמר ספק, u'ba'alas ma'amar safeik, but
רחל's status is doubtful. Either she's definitely אשת שמעון Eshes Shimon or
she's completely אסור assur and she's irrelevant and she's אשת ראובן שלא
היה בעולמו. Eshes Reuven shelo hayah be'olamo. ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי.
V'ein safeik motzi miyedei vaday. So what you're going to do with
רחל will have no impact, will not be good enough for שרה,
because רחל might be irrelevant. Okay. Fine. We're done with that case.
Yes. How is מאמר effected? How is it effective? No, effected. How
is it done? Oh, that's what דוב Dov was asking. Yeah. So
it's basically done through דיבור. dibbur. You know, I did not check.
ואומר לה הרי את. v'omer lah harei at. You know, if you're,
if you, yeah, let me just take a quick look because I
actually have to admit that I did not refresh my memory on
that. Hold on. Let me just refresh my memory on that. I
know we've been talking about it for a long time, but I
just want to make sure that I don't mistake. You're giving her
a declaration? Yeah, well I just want to make sure I was
right about that. Give me a minute. No, no, no, no. So
that's why I'm glad I rechecked because although מאמר sounds like it's
just verbal, it's funny they use that phrase, here it actually does
is an act of קידושין. kiddushin. I'm going to read to you
the רמב"ם Rambam here: מדברי סופרים שלא יבא היבם על יבמתו עד
שיקדש אותה בפני שני עדים בפרוטה או בשוה פרוטה. זה נקרא מאמר.
Mi'divrei soferim shelo yavo hayabam al yevimto ad she'yekadesha bifnei shenei eidim
b'pruta o b'shaveh pruta. Zeh nikra ma'amar. So it's literally like an
act of קידושין, kiddushin, giving כסף kesef in front of two עדים.
edim. ואין המאמר קונה ביבמתו קניין גמור כמו שיתבאר. V'ein ha'ma'amar koneh
bi'yevimto kinyan gamur kemo she'yisba'er. ועושה בה מאמר ביבמתו שלא מדעתה. v'oseh
bah ma'amar bi'yevimto shelo m'da'atah. So here's the בעל כרחה be'al karchah
case, the place we just learned. לא עשה כלום, lo asah klum,
שאין אשה מתקדשת אלא לרצונה. she'ein ishah miskadeshes ela l'rtzonah. So he
really counts calls it like a type of a קידושין. kiddushin. So
it is funny, yeah, I'm sorry. So he says מאמר is you
cannot do יבום דרבנן yibbum d'rabbanan unless you do מאמר and מאמר
is an act of קידושין kiddushin giving a some object of value,
a worth of פרוטה, pruta, you know like a ring in front
of two witnesses. And if you do it against her will, it
doesn't count because it's like a קידושין kiddushin against her will. So
although we use the phrase מאמר, right, I had remembered that. You
know, it is very confusing. We use the phrase מאמר, but it
really, maybe the phrase is in order to undercut so we don't
think that it's really a real קידושין kiddushin because biblically it has
no meaning in the case of a sister-in-law. Yeah. But how can
somebody do that without the other person's consent then? Does she have
to... Yeah, you throw, you throw the money to her but let's
say she doesn't agree to accept the money. It's a good question,
right? How can you... she's still in her property though, right? What?
Some sexual act where... Right. No, but it's... Yeah, but no, but
you can't be קונה koneh something against your will. That's a really
good question, you know, according to רבי, meaning it's one thing to
say if, because what you're saying is the actual act doesn't, never
took place. She never actually acquired the property because you can't be
forced to acquire property against your will. It's a good question. I'll
have to, I'll have to get back to you. She getting to?
What? I, okay, we're going to have to, I have to refresh
my memory on all of this. Okay, so let's take a look.
Let's go further. All right. So the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
יתיב רב מנשיא בר גדי קמיה דרב הונא. Yativ Rav Menashe bar
Gadi kamei d'Rav Huna. So right now our aspirations have adjusted significantly
to get up to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. יתיב רב מנשיא בר
גדי קמיה דרב הונא ויתיב וקאמר. Yativ Rav Menashe bar Gadi kamei
d'Rav Huna v'yativ v'ka'amar. מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama d'Rebbi Shimon?
What's the reason of רבי שמעון that if לוי is born after
יבום, yibbum. רחל is okay? מאי טעמא רבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama Rebbi
Shimon? He's the one that makes sense. כדאמר טעמא, כל יבמה שבאתה
להיתר ולא עמדה עליה שעה אחת באיסור. K'damar ta'ama, kol yevamah she'ba'asa
l'heiteira v'lo amda aleha sha'ah achas b'issura. When לוי was born, רחל
was אשת שמעון. Eshes Shimon. She never had a bad status to
לוי. So אלא ella no, here's what I meant. מאי טעמא דרבנן?
Mai ta'ama d'rabbanan? Okay. What's the reason the rabbis disagree? That makes
so much sense. So אמר קרא ולקחה לו לאשה ויבמה. Amar kra
v'lakacha lo l'ishah v'yibmah. So he should take her for him as
a wife and do יבום yibbum to her. That's the פסוק pasuk
about the act of יבום. yibbum, עדיין יבומים מהראשונים עליה. Adayin yivumim
me'harishonim aleha. So what they read that is... No, here's what I
meant. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai ta'ama d'rabbanan? Okay. What's the reason the
rabbis disagree? That makes some sense. So אמר קרא Amar kra ולקחה
לו לאשה ויבמה. v'likacha lo l'isha v'yibma. So he should take her
as a wife and do יבום yibbum, to her. That's the פסוק
pasuk about the act of יבום. yibbum עדיין יבום מהראשונים עליה. Adayin
yibbum me'harishonim aleha. So what that the way they read that is
that ויבמה, v'yibma, why does it have to say both things? Right?
Why not just say ויבמה v'yibma or ולקחה לו? v'likacha lo? Why'd
it say both languages? To show that even when he takes her
for a wife, even when Shimon married her, Shimon married Rachel, ולקחה
לו לאשה ויבמה, v'likacha lo l'isha v'yibma, her status vis-a-vis Reuven continues
to obtain. Right? So Shimon did יבום yibbum. before Levi was born,
that was ולקחה לו לאשה, v'likacha lo l'isha, but ויבמה v'yibma means,
but she still always remains Reuven's, you know, dead Reuven's wife. And
therefore, when Levi is born, she still has the status of dead
Reuven's wife. Okay. So it's hard to see that in the פסוק,
pasuk, but that's what it's saying. עדיין יבום מהראשונים עליה. Adayin yibbum
me'harishonim aleha. אלא הא דתנן, Ela ha d'tnan, כנסה הרי היא כאשתו
לכל דבר, kinsa harei hi k'ishto l'chol davar, after יבום, yibbum, she's
fully like his wife. ואמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, V'amar Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Chanina, מלמד, melamed, what does that teach you? Top of כף
עמוד א. Kaf amud aleph. שמהגרשה בגט ומחזירה, she'megarsha b'get u'machazira, that
if after a case of יבום, yibbum Shimon did יבום yibbum with
Rachel, he now wants to divorce her, he can divorce her. He
divorces her with a גט. get. And then if he wants to
remarry her, he could remarry her. She's no longer seen as אשת
ראובן eshet Reuven anymore, right? I mean, or whatever, it's an אשת
ראובן eshet Reuven that's מותרת muteret to him because there was once
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum? התם נמי לימא Hatam nami leima
ויבמה, v'yibma, עדיין יבומה מהראשונים עליה. adayin yibbuma me'harishonim aleha. So if
we think her status always still remains as Reuven's widow, so ובעי
חליצה. u'ba'ei chalitza. If Shimon wants to divorce her after יבום, yibbum
so if we're still looking at her as Reuven's wife, so you've
got to do חליצה, Chalitzah. right? That's what Shimon would have had
to have done initially if he didn't want to marry her. So
okay, but if after the act of יבום Yibum we still continue
to look at her as Reuven's widow, so if you now want
to free yourself and divide that relationship, חליצה Chalitzah should also be
required. So it says no, שאני התם shani hatam דאמר קרא d'amar
kra ולקחה לו לאשה, v'likacha lo l'isha, she should become his wife.
כיון דלקחה נעשית כאשתו לכל דבר, Keivan d'lekacha na'aseit k'ishto l'chol davar,
once she's married it's like his total wife, and therefore he doesn't
relate to her as Reuven's widow. He relates to her as his
wife, and therefore it's only about a גט, get, not a חליצה.
Chalitzah אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara so make up
your mind. הכי נמי. hachi nami. Here too, regarding Levi, let her
just be Shimon's wife, not Reuven's wife. Make up your mind. Is
she Shimon's wife or is she Reuven's wife? No, הכתיב ha ktiv
ויבמה, v'yibma, it says that ויבמה v'yibma which means she still is
Reuven's wife. So basically, you have one פסוק pasuk that says she's
fully Shimon's wife and another פסוק pasuk that says she still has
some status of Reuven's wife. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומה ראית?
u'mah ra'ita? What tells you that when it comes to the question
of divorce and חליצה, Chalitzah you say no, she's not Reuven's wife,
only Shimon's, just do a גט? get? When it comes to the
question of Levi's relating to her, and is she אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו, you say oh yeah, she's still a little bit Reuven's
wife. What lets you split it that way? ומה ראית? u'mah ra'ita?
מסתברא, Mistabra, it makes sense. שדי היתירא אהיתירא ושדי איסורא אאיסורא. Shadi
heiteira a'heiteira v'shadi issura a'issura. That the מותר muttar case, meaning when
we're not dealing with any איסורים, issurim, right, he just did יבום
Yibum and now he's divorcing her or whatever, in that case, we'll
see it as basically non-problematic and we'll only look at her as
Shimon's wife. We won't introduce other problems by making her Reuven's wife.
In the case where you started with a problem that she was
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו and then he married her, so then
that problem will still continue to obtain. Okay. Which basically means because
there's something of an ערווה ervah there that's still going to, fundamentally
she's not Reuven's wife, but for the question of a possible ערווה
ervah status, that will still obtain. Okay. Now, ורבי שמעון דאמר v'Rabbi
Shimon d'amar כל הבא מצד היתר לא עמדה עליו שעה אחת באיסור,
kol ha'ba m'tzad heiteir lo amda alav sha'ah achat b'issur, so according
to Rabbi Shimon that says when Levi is born she's totally okay,
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, אחותו מאמו achoto m'imo שנסאה אחיו מאביו, shenesa'ah
achiv m'aviv, let's say you have a maternal sister and then your
paternal brother married her. Okay, you got that? Your paternal brother has
no relation to your maternal sister, right? Because it's a either side.
This was on your right side, this one's on your left side.
So they themselves have no relationship. So they married one another. Okay.
ואחר כך נולד לו אח, v'achar kach nolad lo ach, and then
another brother was born, ומת, תתייבם, tityabbem, why not do יבום? Yibum,
הואיל ובאה מצד היתר, Ho'il u'ba'ah m'tzad heiteir, איסור אחותו. issur achoto.
So since he found her—since he found her בהיתר, be'heiteir, which basically
means, what it's saying is like this, I'll just reframe it in
a simpler way. I don't know why the גמרא Gemara had to
give such a complicated scenario is Rachel was אשת ראובן שלא היה
בעולמו. eshet Reuven shelo hayah b'olamo. She married Shimon and then you
said Levi was born, you only look at her as Shimon's wife.
Why? Why don't you say she's Reuven's, you know, dead Reuven's wife
and Shimon's wife? Somehow you say because she married Shimon, her past
goes away. So the גמרא Gemara says, how about this scenario? Let's
say she was, you know, she was one of them—she was a
sister, right, whatever, a sister that can work. And Reuven and then
Reuven married her and and and then died, and then Shimon did
יבום Yibum and then Levi was born. Why don't you say, oh,
okay, so now she's Shimon's wife, she's no longer a sister. Okay.
As long as he— Right, so the גמרא Gemara says no. איסור
אחות להיכא אזלא? Isur achot leheicha azla? Just because she now did
יבום Yibum with שמעון, she was able to do יבום Yibum. with
שמעון because with שמעון she wasn't a sister. I mean you basically
get the scenario with לוי she's a sister, and with but with
ראובן Reuven and שמעון she's not a sister, okay? So whatever. So
she is basically able to do that. So the גמרא Gemara says
fine, but her status as sister, how did that disappear just because
she married שמעון? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי איסור אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו להיכא אזלא? Hachi nami isur achiv shelo haya be'olamo
leheicha azla? Okay, so how did her status as dead ראובן's Reuven.
wife disappear just because she married שמעון? גמרא Gemara says no no
no. האי איסור דלית ליה היתירא. Hai isur delait lei heiteira. Sister
status never changes. Somebody's status as a sister is always a sister.
האי איסור דאית ליה היתירא. Hai isur de'it lei heiteira. Status of
dead brother's wife is not permanent. How do I know that status
of dead brother's wife is not permanent? Because כל אשה, Kol isha,
because the whole מסכת יבום Masechet Yibum is about how that status
can sometimes be מותר. Mutar. So therefore once this dead ראובן's Reuven
wife marries שמעון, her whole identity as dead ראובן's Reuven wife changes.
The whole fact that שמעון was allowed to marry her shows that
at least for שמעון she was not looked at as an ערווה
Ervah type of a situation. So basically the identity of dead brother's
wife as an ערווה Ervah is more, is less permanent. That's the
whole מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot. So we can say that when she
marries שמעון we no longer look at her in that relationship with
ראובן. Reuven Okay so that was finally the issue of איסור אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. Isur eshet achiv shelo haya be'olamo. All right,
now we get on to a new point. I mean nothing is
really new, but okay. כלל אמרו. Klal amru. Exactly. כלל אמרו. Klal
amru. Actually it's gonna be a little bit easier. כלל אמרו ביבמה.
Klal amru biyevamah. I keep on telling you that and I never
start. כלל אמרו ביבמה, Klal amru biyevamah, כל שהיא איסור ערווה לא
חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Kol shehi isur ervah lo choletzet velo mityabemet. Anybody
who's a real ערווה, Ervah, this is what we've been talking about
until now, the one of the fifteen women, you don't do חליצה
Chalitzah or יבום, Yibum. neither with them or with the צרה, tzarah
you just walk away. איסור מצווה Isur mitzvah ואיסור קדושה, Ve'isur kedushah,
if it's less weighty, it's an איסור מצווה Isur mitzvah which is
going to mean a דרבנן. Derabbanan. If it's only a דרבנן Derabbanan
איסור, Isur, or איסור קדושה Isur kedushah which means an איסור Isur
of כהונה, Kehunah, like a גרושה, Gerushah, so to a כהן. Kohen.
In those cases it's only a לאו Lav or דרבנן. Derabbanan. So
remember, a לאו Lav or דרבנן Derabbanan if you were to do
the קידושין Kiddushin with an איסור לאו Isur lav or an איסור
דרבנן Isur derabbanan it would be binding. And therefore someone, a כהן
Kohen marries someone who he's not allowed to and then he had
a brother and he died, or yeah, or something like that, or
he had a brother who was a חלל, Challal, who married, who
married a גרושה Gerushah or something like that. Okay. So or a
case of אלמנה לכהן גדול. Almanah lekohen gadol. Okay so in those
types of cases, right, so because were a קידושין Kiddushin scenario בדיעבד
Bedi'avad it would be binding, therefore in a case where it's a
יבום Yibum scenario, there still is, you're not allowed to do יבום
Yibum because of the איסורים, Isurim, but there still is the זיקה
Zikah and the obligation and therefore you must do חליצה. chalitzah So
in those cases the איסור קדושה Isur kedushah חולצת ולא מתייבמת. You
do חליצה chalitzah not יבום. Yibum אחותה שהיא יבמתה. Achotah shehi yevimta.
Now, a sister who is also a sister-in-law, which is what, hold
on, let me just remind myself about this. Right. So basically you
have ראובן Reuven and שמעון, or we'll do ראובן and לוי this
time. ראובן and לוי married רחל and לאה. Leah. And רחל and
לאה Leah are sisters, okay? And then ראובן and לוי both died.
So now רחל to לאה Leah is both a sister and a
sister-in-law, right? You got that? Yep. Okay and now a third brother,
זבולון Zevulun or whatever, has to figure out what he's gonna do
with רחל and לאה. Leah. All right? So there's not צרה ערווה,
Tzarah ervah, they were married to different brothers, but now he's got
both of these women facing him. אחותה שהיא יבמתה, Achotah shehi yevimta,
sister who is a sister-in-law, חולצת או מתייבמת. So you know, זבולון
Zevulun can do either חליצה chalitzah. or יבום. Yibum Now we're gonna
see about that because, oh no, wait a minute. Hold on a
minute. Hold on a minute. Oh oh oh okay. So what I
left out, so what's not so clear in the משנה Mishna is
in that case it's not just that רחל and לאה Leah fall
before זבולון, Zevulun, but one of them, let's say רחל, is an
ערווה Ervah to זבולון. Zevulun. I don't know, זבולון's Zevulun daughter, okay?
So in that case זבולון Zevulun can do חליצה or יבום Yibum
to לאה Leah because רחל is out of the picture and he
can do יבום yibbum or חליצה to לאה. Leah. But if רחל
was not his daughter, would he be able to do יבום yibbum
to either of them? Do you remember this? רחל and לאה Leah
sisters from different brothers now fall in front of זבולון. Zevulun. Could
he do יבום yibbum to either one? No. If he were to
do יבום with one, what would he be doing? Having sex with
אשה דזקוקה. isha dezokaka. about אחות זקוקתו, achos zikukaso, right? Because since
he had a quasi קידושין kiddushin to both, in order to consummate
the relationship with one, to have sex with one, is having sex
with a woman who is his quasi-wife's sister. Is that clear? Quasi,
so that's אחות זקוקתו. achos zikukaso. But if רחל is an ערווה
erva to זבולון Zvulun and she's out of the picture, then he
could do חליצה or יבום with לאה. Leah. Okay, so that's what
it's saying. In a case where we're dealing with an ערווה, erva,
that's sort of parenthetical but a key piece that's missing, if we're
dealing with that one of them is an ערווה erva and it's
אחותה שהיא יבמתו, achosa shehi yevamto, she's got a sister who's a
sister-in-law because one of them is an ערווה, erva, חולצת או מתייבמת,
he can do חליצה or יבום to the other. Okay, but if
neither of them is an ערווה erva to זבולון, Zvulun, then he
can't do יבום because that's אחות זקוקתו. achos zikukaso. איסור מצוה, Issur
mitzvah, now what is this איסור מצוה? issur mitzvah? שניות מדברי סופרים.
Shniyos midivrei sofrim. That's דרבנן, de-rabbanan, secondary עריות, arayos, that's what שניות
shniyos means, secondary that are rabbinically forbidden. Okay. איסור קדושה Issur kedushah
is אלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, almanah l'Kohen Gadol, grushah
v'chalutzah l'Kohen Hedyot, a case where it's something relating to being a
כהן. Kohen. Or either married a woman who would always be אלמנה
לכהן גדול, almanah l'Kohen Gadol, right? So if a כהן גדול's Kohen
Gadol brother died and left a wife, that's אלמנה לכהן גדול. almanah
l'Kohen Gadol. Okay, or a brother did an איסור issur and married
a גרושה grushah or he was a חלל challal and married a
גרושה grushah and then he died and now there's an איסור issur
of גרושה. grushah. In those cases, it's because it's not an ערווה,
erva, it's just a לאו lav or דרבנן, de-rabbanan, you still have
to do חליצה. Or another case, ממזר ונתין לישראל, mamzer u'nesin l'Yisrael,
it's a ממזר mamzer and we won't
worry
about נתינים nesinim right now, for ישראל, Yisrael, that's an איסור לאו,
issur lav, ובת ישראל לנתין ולממזר. u'vas Yisrael l'nesin u'l'mamzer.
Okay, or the man is the one with the problem, the
brother is the ממזר mamzer and he's not allowed to
marry the woman
because he's the ממזר. mamzer. She's the ממזר mamzer or he's the
ממזר. mamzer. Yes. Aren't ממזרים mamzerim still חייב chayav in פרו ורבו?
peru u'revu? Yeah, and so marry another ממזר, mamzer, whatever. Okay. So,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's just do a
little bit more. כלל לאתויי מאי? Klal l'asuyei mai? So when it
says כלל אמרו ביבמה, klal amru b'yevamah, so what's that coming to
include? What extra case? It sounds like there's some cases we haven't
mentioned yet. אתא אמר רב פפא לאתויי צרת אילונית Asa amar Rav
Papa l'asuyei tzaras aylonis to tell you, remember that? The צרה tzarah
of an אילונית, aylonis, that that case also, because there's no מצוה
יבום mitzvah yibbum, with the אילונית, aylonis, so the צרה tzarah is
also אסור, assur, וכרב אסי, u'kh'Rav Assi, like רב אסי, Rav Assi,
of course we didn't פסקן pasken that way, but okay. And it's
the exact opposite of what the first גמרא Gemara said. The first
גמרא Gemara says, why did we say fifteen, exactly fifteen? To exclude
צרת אילונית. tzaras aylonis. Here we're saying, why do we say כלל?
klal? In order to include צרת אילונית. tzaras aylonis. All right, anyway.
So the גמרא says, ואיכא דאמרי כל שאיסורה איסור ערווה הוא דאסירי.
v'ika d'amri kol she-issurah issur ervah hu d'assiri. No, maybe someone reads
it this way: we're not focusing on צרה tzarah in this משנה.
Mishnah. We're saying if it's an איסור ערווה, issur ervah, she's אסור,
assur, but היא דאסירה צרתה הלוא איסורה איסור ערווה. hi d'assira tzarasah
halo issurah issur ervah. Oh, thank you. Okay, so thank you very
much. כל שאיסורה איסור ערווה היא דאסירה צרתה הלוא איסורה איסור ערווה.
Kol she-issurah issur ervah hi d'assira tzarasah halo issurah issur ervah. If
it wasn't an איסור ערווה, issur ervah, צרתה לא אסירה, tzarasah lo
assira, then the צרה tzarah would not be אסור. assur. So what's
a scenario where there's somebody that there's no obligation to, but it's
not really about ערווה, erva, that the צרה tzarah, is okay? So
למעוטי מאי, l'mautei mai, what is this coming to sort of address?
אמר רב פפא למעוטי צרת אילונית ודלא כרב אסי, Amar Rav Papa
l'mautei tzaras aylonis u'd'lo k'Rav Assi, the exact opposite of what we
said before. The case of an אילונית, aylonis, it doesn't start with
the fact that she's a צרה, tzarah it starts with it's an
ערווה. erva. It starts with the fact that there's no מצוה יבום.
mitzvah yibbum, So if it's only because there's no מצוה mitzvah יבום,
not because she's an ערווה, erva, in that case the צרה tzarah
will be allowed. And that actually is how we פסקן, pasken, that
an אילונית aylonis is out of the picture, there's no מצוה mitzvah
יבום, but she's not seen as an ערווה, erva, and in that
case the צרה is actually okay.